Guide to the Stanford Presidential Lectures in the Humanities and Arts Recordings
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford Presidential Lectures in the Humanities and Arts recordings
1999-2006
SC1103
Stanford Presidential Lectures in the Humanities and Arts.
2.5 Linear feet
Lecturers represented in this collection include Svetlana Alpers (art history), Elaine Scarry (human rights and the humanities), Lynn Hunt (the novel and human rights), Hazel V. Carby (racializing subjects in post-World War II Britain), Wendy Doniger (self-imitation in ancient India, Shakespeare and Hollywood), Merce Cunningham (in conversation with John Rockwell, dance critic for the NY Times), and Douglas R. Hofstadter (analogy as the core of cognition).
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
The Stanford Presidential Lecture Series in the Humanities and Arts brings the most distinguished scholars, artists, and critics of our time to the Stanford University campus for lectures, seminars, panel discussions, and a variety of related interactions with faculty, students, and the community at large. Funded by the President's Office, and administered under the auspices of the Stanford Humanities Center, these programs explore new roles and relations for the Humanities and Arts in the academic community in the 21st Century.
Past Lecturers: SPRING 2011 Leon Botstein
WINTER 2011 Judith Jamison
FALL 2010 Robert Putnam
SPRING 2010 Mary Robinson
FALL 2009 André Aciman
SPRING 2009 James McPherson
WINTER 2009 Daniel Dennett
FALL 2008 Robert Wilson
Seyla Benhabib
SPRING 2008 Marina Warner
WINTER 2008 Richard Taruskin
FALL 2007 Simon Schama
SPRING 2007 Joan W. Scott
WINTER 2007 Partha Chatterjee This lecture was rescheduled as part of the November, 2007 conference "Ethnicity in Today's Europe"
FALL 2006 Talal Asad
SPRING 2006 Amy Gutmann
WINTER 2006 Douglas Hofstadter
FALL 2005 Lani Guinier
SPRING 2005 Carolyn Abbate
WINTER 2005 Merce Cunningham
FALL 2004 Kwame Anthony Appiah
SPRING 2004 Isabel Allende Wendy Doniger
FALL 2003 Hazel Carby
SPRING 2003 Bruno Latour
WINTER 2002-2003 Peter Brown
SPRING 2002 Lynn Hunt
WINTER 2001-2002 Elaine Scarry
WINTER 2000-2001 Gayatri Spivak
FALL 2000 Roger Chartier
SPRING 2000 Wolfgang Iser
WINTER 1999-2000 Marjorie Garber Homi Bhabha
FALL 1999 Pina Bausch Svetlana Alpers Bei Dao
SPRING 1999 Jacques Derrida Stefan Maul
WINTER 1998-99 Fredric Jameson Beatriz Sarlo Alexander Nehamas
FALL 1998 Henry Louis Gates, Jr. Stephen Jay Gould Karl Heinz Bohrer Wole Soyinka
SPRING 1998 Christo and Jeanne-Claude Peter Eisenman Hélène Cixous Harold Bloom
Description of the Collection
Lecturers represented in this collection include Svetlana Alpers (art history), Elaine Scarry (human rights and the humanities), Lynn Hunt (the novel and human rights), Hazel V. Carby (racializing subjects in post-World War II Britain), Wendy Doniger (self-imitation in ancient India, Shakespeare and Hollywood), Merce Cunningham (in conversation with John Rockwell, dance critic for the NY Times), and Douglas R. Hofstadter (analogy as the core of cognition).
Access Terms
Alpers, Svetlana.; Bausch, Pina.; Carby, Hazel V.; Cunningham, Merce; Derrida, Jacques; Doniger, Wendy.; Gutmann, Amy.; Hofstadter, Douglas R., 1945-; Hunt, Lynn Avery.; Jameson, Fredric; Latour, Bruno.; Nehamas, Alexander; Rockwell, John.; Scarry, Elaine.; Spivak, Gayatri Chakravorty; Stanford Presidential Lectures in the Humanities and Arts.; Arts.; Audiotapes.; Humanities; Humanities--Study and teaching.; Lectures.; Videorecordings.
Collection Contents
- Audiovisual material
  - Video
    - Bohrer, Karl Heinz, "Without Future. The Meaning of Poetic Nihilism for Interpretation, Theater and State", 1998 Nov 9; 98-2102; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam-SP L) (Box 5)
      Karl Heinz Bohrer is Professor for Modern German Literary History at the University of Bielefeld. An accomplished and productive scholar and essayist, he is also editor of the influential journal Merkur, Germany's "journal of European thought" and current affairs. He is one of Germany's leading writers on aesthetics, the aesthetic imagination in literature, and the relationships of literature and culture to the political state. Bohrer was on campus from November 9-10, 1998. He gave a lecture entitled "Without Future: The Meaning of Poetic Nihilism for Interpretation, Theater and State" at Pigott Hall (Bldng. 260) on November 9 at 7:00 p.m.
    - Soyinka, Wole, "Contemporary Literature and the Future of Humanities and Arts", 1998 Nov 30; 98-2103; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam-SP L) (Box 5)
      Wole Soyinka, the Nobel Laureate for Literature in 1986, is a distinguished dramatist, poet, autobiographer, and cultural critic. Born in Nigeria and educated in both his native country and Britain, Soyinka first came to prominence in the 1960s as a dissident artist-activist, whose plays and improvised street theater attacked the follies and cruelties of Africa's early post-colonial leaders. In the years since, Soyinka's work has continued to act as the outspoken conscience to a succession of oppressive regimes in Nigeria as well as other African states, and he has consequently suffered periods of both political imprisonment and exile. Beyond Soyinka's role as the socially engaged man-of-letters, he is also an influential teacher, having taught at a number of universities in Africa as well as in Britain and the United States. Today Soyinka is the Robert W. Woodruff Professor of the Arts at Emory University in Atlanta. Soyinka was on campus from November 30 through December 1, 1998. His lecture "Contemporary Literature and the Future of the Humanities and Arts" was presented at Stanford's Kresge Auditorium (Stanford School of Law) on November 30, at 7:00 p.m.
    - Gates, Henry Louis Jr., "Race and Class/Race in Class", 1998 Oct 12; 98-2101; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam-SP L) (Box 5)
      Henry Louis Gates, Jr. is the W.E.B. Du Bois Professor of Humanities at Harvard University. As one of America's premier scholars on black literature, culture, and history, Gates has championed African-American studies' place in academe. He has been a force in establishing the traditions and cultural context against which black literature should be read and studied. His most recent book, Thirteen Ways of Looking at a Black Man, contains essays about and interviews with influential black men in high-profile positions (e.g., Colin Powell, Louis Farrakhan, Harry Belafonte). Gates was on campus from October 12-13, 1998. He spoke on "Race and Class / Race in Class" at Kresge Auditorium on October 12 at 7:00 p.m.
    - Chartier, Roger, "At the Crossroads Between Textual Criticism and Cultural History: The Return to Literature", 2000 Dec 8; 00-2111; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam-SP L) (Box 6)
      French historian of written culture Roger Chartier inaugurated the Autumn season of the Stanford Presidential Lectures at Stanford on October 16 of 2000. Roger Chartier is currently Directeur d'Études at the École des Hautes Études en Sciences Sociales (Paris) as well as Andrew D. White Professor-at-Large at Cornell University. Since 1969, he has been lecturing and publishing on the relationship between the material history of institutions and the embodied practices which both animate and survive these institutions: in particular, early modern techniques of reading, disseminating and collecting printed information. Roger Chartier presented his lecture entitled "At the Crossroads Between Textual Criticism and Cultural History: The Return to Literature," at the Law School.
    - Jameson, Fredric, "Aesthetic Autonomy in the Age of Late Capitalism", 1999 Mar 22; 99-2104; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam-SP L) (Box 6)
      Fredric Jameson is an internationally renowned Marxist critic. Presently the William A. Lane Professor of Comparative Literature at Duke University, he has long been recognized as a major theorist of modern culture and a master analyst of its relation to socio-economic reality. In recent years Jameson has concentrated on contemporary artistic practices, both popular and elite, and is today best known for the essays collected in Postmodernism, or The Cultural Logic of Late Capitalism (1991), which diagnose late twentieth-century culture as a symptom of the new global economy. Methodologically eclectic, Jameson's critical thought yields unusually subtle studies of aesthetic production, ranging from avant-garde literature and corporate architecture to popular films and video art. Jameson was on campus January 25-26, 1999. He spoke on "Aesthetic Autonomy in the Age of Late Capitalism" at the School of Law, Room 290 on January 25 at 7:00 p.m.
      - Jameson, Fredric, "Aesthetic Autonomy in the Age of Late Capitalism", January 25, 1999; V251.1; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
    - Sarlo, Beatriz, "No Future? Literature and Cultural Politics", 1999 Mar 24; 99-2105; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam-SP L) (Box 6)
      Beatriz Sarlo is one of Latin America's most important cultural critics. Her writings examine the work of literary giants (Jorge Luis Borges: A Writer on the Edge, 1993) and with the same ease, she examines Argentina's every day life to address issues of technology, modernity, fiction and mass media (Escenas de la Vida Posmoderna: Intelectuales, Arte y Videocultura en la Argentina, 1994). Her more recent work is La Maquina Cultural: Maestras, Traductores y Vanguardistas, 1998. Since 1978 she has published Punto de Vista, one of Argentina's most important cultural publications. Sarlo is a professor at the Universidad de Buenos Aires and is a frequent contributor to several Latin American newspapers. She has been a Wilson Center and Guggenheim fellow. Sarlo was on campus February 22-23, 1999. She gave lecture entitled "No Future? Literature and Cultural Politics" at Pigott Hall (Building. 260), Room 113 on February 22 at 7:00 p.m.
      - Sarlo, Beatriz," No Future? Literature and Cultural Politics", February 22, 1999; V251.2; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
    - Nehamas, Alexander, "The Sleep of Reason Produces Monsters", 1999 Mar 8; 99-2106; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam-SP L) (Box 6)
      Alexander Nehamas, born in Greece, studied at Swarthmore and then Princeton, where he earned a Ph.D. in philosophy in 1971. Currently Edmund N. Carpenter Professor in Humanities, Professor of Philosophy, and Professor of Comparative Literature at Princeton, Nehamas is also chair of Princeton's Council of the Humanities. His most recent book is Virtues of Authenticity: Essays on Plato and Socrates (Princeton UP, 1998). Describing how he ended up teaching and writing about philosophy, Nehamas told an interviewer: "My official plan was to go into business and retire at a relatively young age in order to discuss intellectual issues on my yacht. But I never got a yacht, I got tenure instead." Nehamas was on campus March 8-9, 1999. He gave a lecture entitled "The Sleep of Reason Produces Monsters" at the School of Law, Room 290 on March 8 at 7:00 p.m.
      - Nehamas, Alexander, Sleep of Reason Produces Monsters, March 8, 1999; V251.3; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
    - Alpers, Svetlana, "What Are We Looking For? Expectations in Art History", 2000 Feb 15; 99-2110; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam-SP L) (Box 6)
      Svetlana Alpers is an art historian specializing in Baroque painting. She has written controversial books on Rubens, Rembrandt, and Dutch 17th-Century art, and is known for her innovative approaches to theoretical issues of narration and description in the visual arts. Alpers is one of a handful of art historians whose fresh, imaginative methodologies introduced the New Art History to a wider U.S. audience in the 1970s and 1980s. She is professor emerita (History of Art) at the University of California, Berkeley. She gave her lecture at Stanford on November 8, 1999 on "What Are We Looking For? Expectations in Art History."
      - Alpers, Svetlana," What Are We Looking For? Expectations in Art History", 1999 Nov 8; V251.4; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
    - Derrida, Jacques, "The Future of the Profession, or the Unconditional University" (tape #1), 1999 Apr 15-16; 99-2107; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam-SP L) (Box 6)
      Jacques Derrida came into prominence in America because of his association with the school of philosophy and literary criticism known as deconstruction, and it is with deconstruction that he is still most closely identified today. Born in Algeria in 1930 of Algerian Jewish parents, Professor Derrida is Director of Studies at the Ecole des Hautes Etudes en Sciences Sociales, Paris, and Professor of Humanities at the University of California, Irvine. Derrida visited the Stanford campus April 15-16, 1999. He spoke on " The Future of the Profesion, or the Unconditional University (Thanks to the 'Humanities': What Could Take Place Tomorrow)" at Kresge Auditorium.
    - Derrida, Jacques, "The Future of the Profession, or the Unconditional University" (tape #2), 1999 Apr 15-16; 99-2107; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam-SP L) (Box 6)
    - Kasparov, Garry, "Limits of Performance", 99-2108; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam-SP L) (Box 6)
    - Maul, Stefan, "Constructions of Divinity: The Idea of God in Ancient Near East", 1999 May 17-18; 99-2109; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 5)
      Stefan Maul is an internationally renowned Assyriologist. His main area of research is Mesopatamian religion in the first millenium B.C., but he is recognized as a very accomplished scholar in many areas of Assyriology and cuneiform culture. In 1997, Professor Maul was awarded the G. W. Leibniz Prize, the most prestigious scientific prize in Germany, which will allow him generous funding for a scientific project undertaken over the next five years. Maul was on campus May 17-18, 1999. He gave a lecture entitled "Constructions of Divinity. The Idea of God in Ancient Near East" at the Cantor Arts Center Auditorium on May 17 at 7:00 p.m. He also presented a seminar on May 18 entitled "The Magician's Archives".
    - Spivak, Gayatri Chakravorty, "Human Rights and the Humanities", 2001 Feb 12; 77433; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam-SP L) (Box 5)
      Gayatri Chakravorty Spivak is one of the leading literary theorists and cultural critics of our times. She was the Andrew W. Mellon Professor of English at the University of Pittsburgh till 1991, and the Avalon Foundation Professor in the Humanities at Columbia University on 2001. In addition she has taught at Université Paul Valéry, Jawaharlal Nehru University in New Delhi, University of British Columbia, Goethe Universität in Frankfurt, Riyadh University, and Stanford University among others. Her lecture, titled "Human Rights and the Humanities," was presented on February 12 of 2001 at the Law School with a subsequent open discussion at the Humanities Center Annex on February 13, 2001.
      - Spivak, Gayatri Chakravorty, "Human Rights and the Humanities", 2001 Feb 12; V251.5; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
    - Spivak, Gayatri Chakravorty, Human Rights and the Humanities, February 21, 2001; V251.8; 1 videotape(s) (DVCAM) (Box 1)
    - Spivak, Gayatri Chakravorty, Human Rights and the Humanities, February 21, 2001; V251.9; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
    - Scarry, Elaine, "Nine One One: Citizenship in Emergency", February 25, 2002; V251.10; 1 videotape(s) (VHS); Literary theorist and cultural critic Elaine Scarry is the Walter M. Cabot Professor of Aesthetics and the General Theory of Value for the Department of English at Harvard University. She visited Stanford University on February 25-26 of 2002 as part of the Presidential Lectures. Her lecture, entitled "Nine One One: Citizenship in Emergency," was presented at the School of Law on Monday, February 25th, of 2002 (Box 1)
    - Hunt, Lynn, "The Novel and the Origins of Human Rights: The Intersection of History, Psychology and Literature", April 8, 2002; V251. 11; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
      Lynn Hunt is one of North America's most respected historians. Pre-eminent among historians of the French Revolution, she is also known for her theoretical work in European cultural studies. Currently the Eugen Weber Professor of Modern European History at UCLA, Lynn Hunt has taught and lectured internationally, and her books have been translated into a dozen foreign languages. Her lecture, "The Novel and the Origins of Human Rights: The Intersection of History, Psychology and Literature," was presented by the Stanford Presidential Lectures on April 8 of 2002 at the School of Law.
    - Brown, Peter Robert Lamont -- Scholarship and Imagination: The Study of Late Antiquity (copy 1 of 3), January 27, 2003; V251.15; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 2)
      - Brown, Peter Robert Lamont, January 27, 2003; V251.18; 1 videotape(s) (DVCAM) (Box 2)
      - Brown, Peter Robert Lamont, January 27, 2003; 1 optical disc(s) (DVD) (Box 2)
    - Latour, Bruno (1), 4/7/2003; 1 optical disc(s) (DVD) (Box 2)
    - Latour, Bruno (2), 4/7/2003; 1 optical disc(s) (DVD) (Box 2)
    - Carby, Hazel V., "Child of Empire: Racializing Subjects in Post World War II Britain" (copy 1 of 3), November 3, 2003; V251.19; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 2)
    - Doniger, Wendy, February 23, 2004; V251.22; 1 videotape(s) (DVCAM) (Box 2)
    - Allende, Isabell, 5/10/2004; 1 videotape(s) (DVCAM) (Box 2)
    - Appiah, Kwame Anthony [Tape 1 of 2], November 1, 2004; V251. 23; 1 videotape(s) (MiniDV) (Box 2)
    - Appiah, Kwame Anthony, 2004; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 2)
    - Cunningham, Merce, March 9, 2005; V251.24; 1 videotape (Betacam SP L) (Box 3)
      - Merce Cunningham, March 9, 2005; V251.25; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 3)
      - Cunningham Dance Foundation, March 9, 2005; V251.26; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 3)
      - Merce Cunningham, March 9, 2005; V251.27; 1 videotape(s) (DVCAM) (Box 3)
      - Merce Cunningham, March 9, 2005; V251.28; 1 videotape(s) (DVCAM) (Box 3)
    - Abbate, Carolyn, May 2, 2005; V251.29; 1 videotape(s) (DVCAM) (Box 3)
    - Hofstadter, Douglas R., "Analogy as the Core of Cognition", February 6, 2006; V251.31; 1 optical disc(s) (DVD) (Box 3)
      - Douglas R. Hofstadter, February 6, 2006; 1 optical disc(s) (DVD) (Box 2)
      - Douglas R. Hofstadter [Tape #1], February 6, 2006; V251.30; 1 videotape(s) (DVCAM) (Box 3)
    - Gutmann, Amy, 4/24/2006; 1 optical disc(s) (DVD) (Box 2)
    - Asad, Talal, 10/9/2006; 1 optical disc(s) (DVD) (Box 2)
    - Cronon, William, 11/8/2006; 1 optical disc(s) (DVD) (Box 2)
  - Audio
    - Dao, Bei, 1999 Nov 29; 3.47; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
      The third and final lecturer scheduled to appear in the Fall Quarter series is Bei Dao, considered to be one of China's foremost poets. He is also known as Zhao Zhenkai, but has used the pseudonym Bei Dao since the late 1970s. In 1989, he was accused of helping to incite the protests in Tiananmen Square and consequently forced into exile. He has published numerous volumes of poetry and short stories, several of which have been translated into English. He was also one of the founders of Today (Jiantian), a literary magazine that provided a venue to emerging authors and poets, including Bei Dao himself. Bei Dao, who now lives in the U.S., has been a visiting scholar at the International Institute and the Center for Chinese Studies. He is currently in residence at the University of California Davis, and working on a collection to be entitled "Unlock." Bei Dao, accompanied by his translator, Eliot Weinberger, gave his lecture and a reading in Chinese and English at Stanford on November 29, 1999.
    - Bausch, Pina. Tape 1 of 2, October 18, 1999; 3.45; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
    - Bausch, Pina. Tape 2 of 2, October 18, 1999; 3.46; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
    - "Past Dependencies." Moderator: Hans Ulrich Gumbrecht. Presentations: Joseph Raz, Elizabeth Spelke, Peter Goodrich. Tape 1 of 9, November 5, 1999; 4.1; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 4)
    - "Past Dependencies." Moderator: Hans Ulrich Gumbrecht. Presentations: Peter Goodrich, Gary Hatfield. Discussion: Joseph Raz, Elizabeth Spelke, Peter Goodrich, Gary Hatfield. Tape 2 of 9, November 5, 1999; 4.2; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 4)
    - "Past Dependencies." Discussion: The Past as Constitution of Identity? Moderator: Hans Ulrich Gumbrecht. Presentations: Joseph Raz, Elizabeth Spelke, Peter Goodrich, Gary Hatfield. Also: Different Areas/Different Pasts? Moderator: Robert Weisberg. Presentations: Avner Greif, Klaus Luderssen, David Harvey. Tape 3 of 9, November 5, 1999; 4.3; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 4)
    - "Past Dependencies." Moderator: Robert Weisberg. Presentation: David Harvey. Discussion: Avner Greif, Klaus Luderssen, David Harvey. Also: Presentations: Bin Wong. Tape 4 of 9, November 5, 1999; 4.4; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 4)
    - "Past Dependencies." Moderator: Robert Weisberg. Presentations: Bin Wong, Denise Schmandt-Besserat, Jochen Horisch. Discussion.Tape 5 of 9, November 5, 1999; 4.5; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 4)
    - "Past Dependencies." Moderator: Mark Granovetter. Presentations: Wlad Godzich, Ricardo Benzaquen, Charles Rosen. Discussion. Tape 6 of 9, November 6, 1999; 4.6; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 4)
    - "Past Dependencies." Moderator: Mark Granovetter. Discussion: Wlad Godzich, Ricardo Benzaquen, Charles Rosen. Presentations: Niklas Damiris, Robert Frank. Tape 7 of 9, November 6, 1999; 4.7; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 4)
    - "Past Dependencies." Moderator: Mark Granovetter. Presentation: Robert Frank. Discussion: including: Niklas Damiris. Moderator: Kathleen Sullivan. Presentation: Richard Posner. Tape 8 of 9, November 6, 1999; 4.8; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 4)
    - "Past Dependencies." Moderator: Kathleen Sullivan.Presentation: Richard Posner. Discussion: including: Erika Frick, Jack Rakove, Richard Rorty, Hayden White. Tape 9 of 9, November 6, 1999; 4.9; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 4)
    - Bhabha, Homi K., March 6, 2000; 4.10; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 4)
      Homi K. Bhabha gave a lecture at Stanford on March 6, 2000. Born in Bombay in 1949, Homi Bhabha received his D. Phil. in Oxford. After teaching English at Sussex University from 1978-1994, he began his tenure at the University of Chicago in 1994 where he is now the Chester D. Tripp Professor of Humanities. Widely know for his work in colonial theory, post-colonial theory and cosmopolitism, Bhabha is considered one of the world's foremost authorities on international cultures. Some of his publications are The Location of Culture (Routledge, 1994) and the edited volume Nation and Narration (Routledge, 1990).
    - Iser, Wolfgang, April 3, 2000; 4.11; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 4)
    - Garber, Marjorie, January 11, 2001; 4.12; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 4)